Music
Greetings, Dragon Slayers, Giant Killers.
You are listening to the 130th episode of Lord of Spirits podcast.
Why you're still here is a mystery to me.
I have nowhere else to go.
I know, there's a thousand channels and there's nothing on.
Nevertheless I am Father Andrew Stephen Damick and with me is the professor and professor
here.
to the stars. I used that joke last time, but I still like it. Father Stephen D. Young.
And we're not live. We're celebrating Christmas like most of you. Father Stephen is getting...
Is it Chinese takeout or Vietnamese? What is it you normally get on Christmas?
So we go... You have to go to the Chinese restaurant and eat there with the local jewelry.
Oh, eat in. Eat in. I see.
Okay. All right.
The whole Jewish community is there... I'm not joking.
This is not some kind of anti-Semitic slur.
No, you're an accurate thing.
Very Catholic.
So I'm sure there are always Jewish people there. Yeah gather together
Yeah, yeah, so I've told that's for two reasons number one. They're open but number two actually
Apparently you could find kosher food pretty easily at a Chinese buffet
Although I feel like Chinese buffets have been going down over the years in quality
Is that the case with yours or is it just here in Pennsylvania?
It's one of those there, pencil.
I mean, the one I used to go to in Hamlin, Pennsylvania was...
literally a Chinese buffet next door to a closed pet store.
Wow. This is amazing beginning for this episode. This is just a fact. I'm not saying anything.
I'm not conjecturing. I'm just saying. Factually, that's where it was located.
Northeastern Pennsylvania. How we love you. Well, the great gatekeeper Mike only plays wingspan
again is not going to be taking your calls this time because as I mentioned this is a pre
recorded episode, that said, over the years, it is unacceptable and therefore must not
be kept. The gate is shut. We've gotten a lot of questions about exactly what it means
when God appears bodily in the Old Testament. And we've said, this is the incarnate Christ.
We have resisted using this word pre-incarnate. This is kind of a mind-bending thing for human
beings to consider so.
So for our Christmas episode, we're actually going to be dedicating the whole time to exploring
this question closely.
So, you know, let's start with a spicy take father.
You say that time and space don't exist.
Does that mean that lunch time is also an illusion?
Yes.
All right.
And further, that means there's a cordillary.
You can eat and drink whatever you want at any time you want.
any because time and space and calories.
Yeah, do not.
is just kilo count.
You want to have pancakes at 8 p.m. do it.
Yesterday.
You want to have a double Western bacon cheeseburger
from Carl's Jr. for breakfast.
Do it at 8 a.m. doesn't matter.
Plus you're not fooling anybody by putting tomato juice
or orange juice in your vodka.
You're still drinking early in the morning.
Wow, this is having a very very dark...
beginning today.
So.
But yeah, so we are, we are talking about the
incarnation.
Is that dark?
People are celebrating.
A good.
I was let's, let's say that.
Yeah, that sounds good.
Yes.
We are talking about the incarnation.
Brunch.
This is Christmas.
We're not good.
Is about drinking.
The Puritans told me so.
That's why they don't celebrate it.
That's true.
As as as as as maybe not by your definition, but
friend of the show Deacon Sarah from Richard
would say have the kind of crystal he is all of a crumb well would outlaw. He may be your friend,
but it's not your friend. The man of the man of a thousand aliases. It's true. It's true. But yeah,
we should say that you're not going to walk away from this episode like understanding the incarnation
or having explored every single dogmatic aspect of it. Yes, we're going to fail at our mission terribly.
Yes, bye.
But the point here is to talk about this particular question of the incarnation as it relates
to time which is not an easy thing to master.
And I think largely, am I correct in thinking that the church fathers largely don't address
this kind of directly?
I think they do.
It's just those aren't the passages people read.
Okay.
Yeah.
So this is one of those things because on my Twitch stream lately I've been getting
a lot of questions about particular things in St. Augustine.
And when I keep having to point out is that people don't actually read St. Augustine.
Right?
Our Protestant friends quote mine St. Augustine.
Yeah.
Bye.
they invented that, right? So when you point out just basic things, like they're saying,
say to Gustard believed that everyone is born with the guilt of Adam's sin and you point out,
you know, hey, when say to Gustard talks about sin, does he talk about it in terms of
juridical guilt? No, he doesn't, right? Or like our last episode would be pointed out, you know,
he says pretty clearly that God doesn't control human wills when he's talking about astrology
in the city of God.
So how are you saying he's a predestinarian?
Yeah.
Um,
Bunches of these things.
And so,
even leaving aside
all the stuff of the church fathers
that isn't translated,
because people don't find it interesting,
or just haven't gotten to it.
Uh,
even what is translated into English,
people read on certain subjects.
Great.
looking for and not others and the stuff that seems confusing. They don't read. And so you
get this phenomena that happens to the host of this program a lot, where we say something,
we don't give a thousand tedious footnotes. How dare we? A bunch of people laugh out of
me, they're like, you're speculating and making this stuff up. And then someone who's actually
red things pops up in his life.
like, uh, no, actually this is, and, you know, much like the Samson thing where we literally
always say about him what the church fathers on the scripture say about him.
Yes.
This happened when I gave that, that, uh, talking involving Nietzsche at Pajofast, right,
almost immediately somebody popped up in the, in the YouTube comments when he released it
and said, this is just what I was even speculating.
This isn't worth a nice teaching.
And then it took about five minutes and a Romanian person.
was like this is all from the Philikol, he had started listing like authors. So all that is to say,
yes, actually, if you go and study how the church fathers talk about the eternity of God,
you actually do get what we're going to be trying to convey tonight.
Yeah, and also just the obligatory plug for
George Montserrat, these these time and man, which deals with a lot of this and kind of related contextual stuff.
Yeah. So, yeah, this is not... this is actually something that they're fairly, but you have to be reading for it.
And if you have other presuppositions, right, this is the other thing.
You come to the text of the presupposition.
that eternity means an endless succession of moments in the past and future. We'll talk more about
this as we go forward. But if that's what you're just assuming eternity means, then whenever you read
the word eternity in an English translation of the church fathers, you're just going to assume it
means that. Yeah, endless time. People don't take the step of saying, okay, how is this author using
this word. It's not necessarily what.
But I think this word, quote unquote, dictionary definition means.
Yeah, I mean, it's much like the way that, frankly, a lot of fundamentalists and many other
Protestants read the Bible.
Like, well, that's what it says.
You know, they'll just point at something like that.
Yeah.
Even when they disagree, both sides will say that.
Because they're just making those assumptions based on their presuppositions.
So we have to, if we're going to talk about...
what it means for Christ's humanity to become eternal by being united to the
second person of the Trinity which is another way of stating our topic for this
evening. We have to break that down. We have to start with, okay what does eternal
mean? What does it mean to be eternal? Because there are multiple definitions of
that or multiple
ways of understanding what that could mean that are mutually exclusive. So that's where
we're going to start. We'll start with what does it mean for something to be eternal?
What does it mean for something to be timeless? We're not talking about Tony Storm primarily
here. That's a reference that Father Andrew didn't get but he just chuckled at anyway.
I feel like I'm getting it.
Keep talking.
It's time it's familiar to me, but I don't know.
I doubt it, but okay.
Okay.
Yes, and so we do begin with time and space don't exist.
I think actually I think it flipped a switch in my head that was like Tony Stark, but maybe it
turns out this is not the case.
Yes.
So, uh...
What do we say, time and space don't exist, right?
People say what?
Or they say, dude, because they're intoxicated.
We have to even break that down a little bit to what does it mean to exist?
And
Here's a teaser by the time we're done with this first half.
We're going to talk about the fact that God doesn't exist.
Dun dun dun.
So, which the church fathers say that?
Yes.
Yeah, say, Maxivus the confessors is exactly that.
But so what does it mean to exist, right?
And what we usually mean
by exist in our common parlance is something exists if it exists externally to a subject.
So we've talked about this before on the show and I know we're already getting...
Some people's brains explode eat.
But if I look at the wall of my office here, as we've said on the show before, the color,
which I can't describe because I'm a dude.
But it's not one of those ancient people couldn't see blue.
Father Stephen can't see.
no no it's just a kind of green gray thing that i
sure there's a name for it, but I don't know it because I'm a dude. But anyway, that color
does not actually exist because if I wasn't here looking at it, right, color, remember
the mantis shrimp, color only exists as a relationship of perception. Right. There are
certain wavelengths of light.
that are reflecting off of that wall, striking the human eye in a certain way to produce that color.
Right, but no human eyeball, no color, no light in the room, no color. Right. Right.
So the color doesn't have external existence. The wall itself does.
Like it turned off all the lights, closed my eyes, tried to walk through the wall, I will hit the wall.
Hahaha.
100 out of 100 times.
Yeah, I mean the things that you see are literally a thing your brain is doing.
That's what seeing is.
Right.
How you're interpreting it.
But there is an actual existence out there.
Right. It's not a hallucination.
Right. If it was a hallucination I could walk through the wall.
Okay.
So we'd say the wall exists.
The color of the wall does not exist in the same sense at least.
The color of the wall exists in my consciousness.
And specifically my consciousness,
because another person with different eyes looking at it,
might see a different color.
Right.
We could all think of like that goofy dress photo
and things like that where there things where some people
see something one way and other people see something
another way even though they're looking at the same thing.
Or even that yinny moral thing that is an oral question.
Yeah.
Yeah, or just you know, hey somebody who's red green color blind, right?
Because my walls are kind of greenish, right? They're gonna see it.
They're gonna be like greenish. There's gray, right?
So that's what we mean by exist, right? And so when we say time and space don't exist
what we're saying is that
the categories of time and space are
are catac...
allegories of human experience, like color, right? And not things that objectively exist
without any people there, right, without an observer, right? And we've all, frankly,
Note
notice this with time.
Right?
People who want to argue with me on this point would say, well, no, time exists.
Time passes at one second per second, right?
It's a uniform rate, dot, dot, dot, of, dot.
Of course, we know for physics, it doesn't move in a uniform rate.
It moves in different relative rates, right?
But even beyond that, you would be out of, just in our own personal experience, right?
Because that's what we're talking about.
It's our personal experience.
You've had periods of time that seem to take longer or that seem to be shorter.
Even though objectively an hour is an hour, right, sometimes an hour if you're really
involved in something seems to go by very quickly and sometimes an hour if you're less
involved like you're sitting in a Zoom meeting, seems to drag on forever.
Right. Even though quote, unquote, objectively an hour is an hour.
And again, we're not going to go at all the physics because neither of us is a physicist
and that's just cringe for people to try to do that.
But, right, hopefully folks have added up high school slash college physics that they know,
you know, at least some basic Einstein stuff, that the experience to difference in the passage
of time could become quite literalized in certain circumstances.
So, it also that time and space as categories are intimately connected.
So part of the issue here is that this is just a thing that's hard to wrap our head around.
Yeah.
So, there is, for example, scientifically an edge of space.
Yeah, which is like, we know that's true, and they'll say things like the universe is expanding,
but into what?
Like is there space beyond space that it's expanding into?
Right.
Well, that's what people assume.
Yeah.
That there's just sort of this endless succession of points in all directions, right?
But that is actually not the case scientifically.
is an edge of space.
And our brain can't wrap our head around that because we're like, okay, so you come to the edge of space, right?
We're at the very edge of space
Well, so what if you go one inch further
And you get told there is no inch further you're at the end of space you're at the end of inches
Right, and our headcat wrap around it.
And this is the same problem.
problem we have, right, to tie this back to our point tonight, right, that we have thinking
about time and creation, for example.
Right, so if we say, okay, God, God created time at space, obviously, right, he created
everything, right?
So we're going to say God created time and space.
Okay, so God creates time.
What about like 10 seconds before that?
Right?
And our brain can't fathom there were no seconds before that.
Because if there were 10 seconds before that, then that would be the beginning of time.
Right.
So the finitude of time and space is something that's very difficult to wrap your brain around.
But the fa-
fact, the fact that the human brain has trouble, right, is a, is a sorry William Lane Craig.
This is one of the, if we're getting past him being the, the frackedly wrong panheretic
to William Lane Craig the bad philosopher.
He's the kind of guy who says that...
If you can't, if something is, it doesn't work for hew and logic.
If you can't wrap your brain around it, then it's not true.
Wow. I mean, yes.
I would think that that should be classified as extreme hubris.
Just to put it mildly.
Well, he believes God can't do logically impossible things.
Wow. You see, I'm telling you, the guy is wrong about everything.
There's nothing he is right about.
So you could say, well, he's right that A got exists.
It's like, well, yeah, but the one he thinks exists is the wrong one.
The one he thinks exists doesn't.
So, yeah.
But contra that seems like anyone's sensible,
especially anyone coming from the Christian tradition.
would say, well obviously there are things regarding God, especially, that the human mind cannot comprehend.
The fact that something is incomprehensible about God to the human mind
actually may be evidence that it's true. It may actually go the other way.
That we should expect God at his ways to be beyond human comprehension because he told us they were.
Yeah.
And so that's okay.
My ways are higher than your ways,
except for when you don't understand them.
We're simply, yes.
Well, that was just true,
because he was talking to broadsage people.
See, that were modern people.
We're so smart.
We have the science and the logics.
And so now we can understand everything.
I would just go the next step,
go full, full haggle would be like,
we're practically God ourselves, you know?
Yeah, so that said, the actual reason why we can't comprehend those things.
Right, so we've kind of made two points so far.
We're trying to take this slowly and deliberately because I know it's brain breaking.
Point 1, time and space exist really within human subjectivity.
within human experience, not external to it.
And number two,
that they have borders like a beginning and an end,
right, there's borders to space.
There are borders or endpoints to time.
And that's true even though the human brain can't really
Rappers.
head around the fact that there are borders to space or time.
And that's because, right?
The second point is because of the first point.
Because space and time exist within the realm of human experience, they're part of the grid
through which we understand all of our experiences.
So
categories of time and space are part of the grid before and after. Right?
Near-far, right? Movement, change, all of these things are parted parcel of how we
experience and interpret everything we experience. So when you're asked to
imagine experiencing something that falls outside of that grid, you can't imagine
understand it.
Right. We don't have the categories of thought for it.
Yeah. We don't have another set of categories that we would have to use it to.
Right.
And so yeah, just basic things like our understanding of cause and effect.
or say you cause effect presupposes number one.
a temporal sequence, right? Like, if one thing happens, and then another thing happens
a hundred years later, and you want to say thing one, cause thing two, you've got to establish
a whole chain of events, right? Like all set up all the dominoes in between the two,
right? To connect them, right? Because we assume there's got to be a connection
in time. And if they happen on other sides of the planet, right, then, yes, there are
sides to the planet. Just throw it straight, it's flat earthers. You've, right, then you're
going to have to establish, right, in that chain of causes also crossing the distance,
right? So what or something is going to have to go from one place to the other place and
carry that causal, that causal.
right? And you know, David Hume came out and said, cause an effect don't strictly speaking
exist because they're not strictly speaking observable, right? But even he admitted, but yeah,
you kind of have to assume cause an effect or, you know, you can't live and function.
Wow. Right, like as a human, right? So even someone who wants to try to make the argument.
Right?
Can't really escape these categories of thought and experience.
Right? You can't really escape or get outside of that grid.
And so when we're saying that time and space aren't things,
not the modern usage, that's not a thing.
thing, but in the very literal sense of you can't like grab some space.
or hold on to some time.
Right. What we mean is that they're the description of our relationship between things.
Right. If you're talking about time before and after, for example, if you're talking about space over under.
Right.
Uh...
We all accept...
So, for example, space, spatial terms, we all kind of accept that those are relative.
Right?
It's like you're a flat-erther, and then you're like, how there be people on bottom of globe.
But, like, we accept that if you got space, there's not an up and a down really.
Right.
like South America is South America because it's like toward the South pole, not because
it's on the bottom of the earth.
It's funny to me how in almost every sci-fi movie or TV show, the shapes never go up or
down.
They always turn left or right or turn around or whatever.
You know, like you're still going to use your advantage in the Bhutara Nebula.
You
Yeah, they're treated like sailing ships basically.
Yeah, well, there's an up and a down.
When they approach Earth, Earth is always oriented north to south, you know.
Right.
Like a globe.
Yeah, yeah, there's no reason to, right?
I mean, at Antarctica, you could say it's the top of the world just as easily.
because top and bottom it's completely relative.
Right?
So we all accept that.
Again, unless you're like a defiant flat-erther.
We all accept that those things are kind of relative.
And like we said, we start getting into physics.
You kind of start finding out that weird things happen with time, too.
But we're not again here to talk about science.
per se, we're here to talk about God.
So, we're talking about eternity, what we mean by eternity.
We're really talking about what it means when we ascribe that quality to God.
We say that God is eternal.
And so, if you've been wondering why so far we've been talking about time and space instead
just
time, it's because hopefully as you've already seen the two are intimately connected and
thinking about it in terms of space is at least a little easier than thinking about it in
terms of time for us.
So we're going to start using space and then analogize from that over to time to try
to help explain this.
So when we're talking about space, spatial categories.
and ideas like distance in space.
We're speaking from the point of view
of a finite creature,
because everything created is finite.
And so for us,
we,
and everything else we know
that exists right from other people.
to chairs, to globes, to windows, to atmospheric gases, right?
When we say those things exist, part of their finite existence is that they fill a certain series of points in space.
They occupy a series of points in space. It can be big or small, right? Relatively more, relatively fewer points in space.
No, we're
not getting a Dizino's paradox right now of how much space is a point. But the idea being
whatever unit of measurement you want to use, right, there is a finite quantity of space
taken up by the volume of the object, right. And for it to occupy as a finite object,
human body for it to occupy.
another series of points in another place, that finite object has to cross the
intervening points in space. And then it can go and occupy another set of points
in space. And going from occupying one set of points in space through the
intervening points in space to occupy another set of points in space is what we
called movement.
That is something moving and it moves because it's finite.
And so it has to cross all of those points in space in between to get from one to the other.
And we can then measure that movement in various ways as to direction, as to continuity.
Most common one we use is speed.
Right, how much time is elapsed while it is crossing from one set of points to the other?
and crossing the points in between.
Okay, so that's your basic, right?
Your finite objects which includes pretty much every created thing, right?
So, then we talk about God,
and we say that God is omnipresent.
So as God's eternity is to
time God's omnipresence is to space that's the analogy we're making here. So we say God is omnipresent
and what do we mean by that? Because there are different ways that someone could see that.
Yeah I mean when we think about presence we probably think about like a human person you know being
in the same room with us.
And then we say, God is everywhere.
Are you buying new?
nearby points in space. Yes. Yeah. And so you could say, well, okay, someone could imagine
like the the the Monty Python prayer and meaning of life that God is just really, really big.
That is just huge. And he sort of spread out through the whole universe. Right. So so he's occupying
sort of all of the points.
He's just so big that he occupies all of the points in space, right?
And that's what we mean when we say he's omnipresent.
But that's kind of weird if you push out it a little bit.
Yeah, I mean, in some ways it kind of reduces God to being like a pagan God, just a really
big thing.
Yes, he's still a thing, right?
He's just the biggest thing.
And also it it definitely depersonalizes him right because it's
Right like
Okay, there's there's some
Element of him in this room
Right, but does that correspond to like a human toe right does that right? You know what I mean like that's not a
right and
That isn't really the idea.
There's some piece of God here that we...
could reach out and theoretically touch is that usually what we mean when we're talking
about God's omnipresence? We usually mean he's there in person, right? Like, as in you
could interact with him, right? The whole God as it were. Yes. Someone could also say,
Well, it just means that God is everywhere it wants.
Right, like the whole earth.
is just packed with a nearly infinite number of identical Jesus' right? Just sort of all at once
right? So that everybody can interact with him right? Like I again that's that's weird right?
Because that makes it seem like there's just more than one of him or like instead of the holy
Trinity you've got.
that nearly infinite number of persons that all have a hive mind or something, which is not the doctor to the Trinity at all.
Yeah, I mean, this kind of reminds me of the joke with the father, Guido Sarducci, joke where he says, you know, if God is invisible in a spirit, and I'm made in the image of God, shouldn't I be able to turn invisible?
It's this kind of thinking, right?
Which I mean, I guess it makes sense, right?
Because this is the finite human...
mind trying to grapple with the presence of the power of God, you know, the infant. Yeah.
Yeah. So, yeah, that's weird, right? The, so what do we mean then, right? And we would definitely
say that even though people will talk about the Holy Spirit moving
or something, they're using that as an analogy.
Yeah.
We don't literally think God has to cross
intervening space.
Like we wouldn't say,
I, in the liturgy, say Christ isn't our midst,
and then they say the same thing two minutes later
in Metare, Louisiana,
and that means Christ has two minutes to get
from here to there, right?
like, no, obviously, that's dumb, right?
That's that one.
Right?
God has it after like move from place to place
and cross all the intervening space,
where you can like measure his speed, right?
So that doesn't make any sense, right?
Yeah.
And that part really brings us to the crux of the matter
is that we're talking about God's omnipresent.
So we're really talking about its effect
that unlike us, he's not finite.
Right, it was just an apophatic thing to say.
He's not this.
Right.
He's not finite, meaning what we're really saying is, unlike us, he is not occupying a
particular set of points in space.
Right.
Even all the points.
Even all of them.
Right.
He is not everybody to say.
So what we're ultimately saying is, this is what Saint Duitieru's St. Aley means when
He talks about God's attributes being super essential.
Is that...
What we really mean when we say God is omnipresent is that these spatial categories that we use to describe our own experience and to describe
you know other objects in the world that we encounter those categories don't apply to God.
Because God is not a thing in the world.
He doesn't exist in the way we do and the way created things do.
Right.
So, if we understand that regarding spatial categories, they just don't apply to God.
That's what we mean.
Now let's turn to ideas of eternity, right?
And there are some weird views of eternity, but here it comes again, Plato brain.
of Western thought has got this idea
about eternity, at least the more subtle ones, the actual better ones. So, you know, we're
going to say Plato was wrong, but he was more of the right track than some folks like William
Lane Craig. So in terms of what eternity is.
How did I know that when we do a, whenever we do an episode on Christology, on any level,
You're gonna mention William Lane Craig and...
of times. I'm going to relentlessly bash William Lane Craig. Yes. Dr. Craig, if you're listening,
please send us an email. We'd love to hear from you. No, he won't. I know. He does this whole,
he doesn't debate his fellow Christians thing. Yes. So he does get called out his heresies. But as I've
said many times, I don't consider him to be my fellow Christians. So he could debate me. He would
refine on any topic.
So yeah, so Plato's idea of eternity is essentially stasis.
Yeah.
This is a problem, right?
But the reason for that is, what is time?
In terms of how we use it, the way we most commonly use it is a way of measuring change.
Think cooking time.
Think how old is somebody.
And so for Plato, timelessness then must equal changelessness.
Because you would have to have time in order to have change.
Therefore, for anything that is truly eternal, has to be completely unchanging, and therefore
unmoving, because even movement is a kind of change.
Movement requires time, speed.
So you get this idea of stasis.
No movement, no change, no activity, no nothing.
And this in the Platonic period that is not St. Augustine's fault, but which was triggered by St. Augustine in the West, gets adapted into particularly in Latin theology, the concept of God.
And...
Well, it may not immediately be obvious why that's a problem because you may be saying to me well, well no God doesn't change
And that that's correct right God doesn't change
and
We just said God doesn't move per say in a literal sense right
So that's not a problem because a big problem when you get to God doesn't act
God doesn't do anything.
Yeah.
Because this is where you get the idea and the theology of
Absolute divine simplicity
For example, yeah
That God is act is purest. Yeah, and you know I'm a fancy lad because I could have just said pure act in English
But no, I use the lat for some reason the the Latin phrase is pure is the one
Yes.
Right. And so this idea, right, that God is unchanging, builds in then the kind of platonic
idea that leads to the development in Latin theology of the idea of created grace. And
this is why Latin theologians were being consistent.
reject St. Gregory Pala Mas.
It will even accuse him of being a polytheist
in a heretic,
because they have this firm belief
that God cannot act,
and therefore he needs a created intermediary
through which to act.
Yeah.
So for Plato, this is simple,
but you can see how as Plato gets adapted into religion,
like in Neoplatonism,
You get this kind of quasi-nostics here.
of emanations from the actual God who is in stasis.
And the things that are acting are sort of derivative.
You can see how that deforms your view
of the Holy Trinity.
You can see, if you're just thinking about it,
a little bit.
You can see how you get these ideas.
Created intermediaries, you can see where you get
Areanism, all of this stuff is...
In some sense it's fruit of this poison tree, right?
This idea that eternity is some kind of stasis,
and therefore God and true eternity cannot directly act,
cannot do anything, cannot move vis-a-vis creation at all.
Now, what's a better way than of thinking about God's eternity?
Right.
And this is why we spent the time talking about omnipresence.
So, just like the way we think about space and distance,
the way we think about time is conditioned in our human experience by the fact that we're finite.
In the same way that we exist at a certain series of points in space,
space, we exist at a certain point in time.
That point in time just sort of keeps rolling forward, right?
Time zero.
Yeah.
See, there's an ex-generation episode around this point.
You're welcome.
Um, yeah, I just was that one direction.
And you say, well, okay, I just was in one direction.
I could move in lots of directions in terms of space.
Well, you could, but imagine this.
Imagine someone did a bunch of research on you, uh, like
volunteers doing right now as we speak.
Um,
and decided to map your movements for your whole life.
They could draw one line with an arrow at the end
and trace all of your movements your whole life.
So your physical movements in space
are not all that different than your movement through time.
In fact, as we said, they're connected, right?
And you only experience them in one direction.
because we're finite. And as we mentioned time, we think of mostly terms of growth and change,
right? The sundial, the shadow moves, right? The position of the sun changes. And we use time to
describe right seconds minutes and hours are kind of arbitrary divisions right
at a very long time ago, that's why they're in base 60 math.
Right?
But there are returring divisions.
If you have to define a second, one-sixtieth of a minute.
Right?
You can only, they only make sense with reference to each other.
There isn't something out there that's described by it.
Yeah.
But so, the place where we start, then, to understand God's eternity, is that God does not
exist at a point in time.
Right?
Nor does, as we said in space, does He exist sort of simultaneously at all points in time?
He doesn't exist at a point in time, any more than He exists at a particular point in space.
Right.
Because he doesn't...
exist in that way. He's not finite. That also means, right, for God to do exit one time and do
why at another time. He does not need to cross the intervening moments in time. He doesn't have to
sit and wait. Right. Any more than he has to go from one place to another place and cross all the
He puts it time.
He got his not sort of spread out through time.
Obviously, right, there's part of a mere.
And then three days from now,
it'll be a different part of God, right?
That's just that temporal categories
do not apply to God.
Now, if we follow this out,
this is our ultimate sorry Calvinus.
But let's not pick on Calvinus.
This is also sorry Armenians.
Yeah because it's all
based on this kind of idea that God is subject to linear time, that God is somewhere along the timeline,
that time is bigger than God, so to speak. Not only does God exist at a point in time,
he exists at the same point of time that I do at the same time that I do.
Yeah, so he's like making predictions, it's just he's way better at it.
Yes, right. So if someone told you, if someone asked you where is God,
Right?
If you ask someone...
Where is God?
Their response was, well, he's up in heaven.
Like he's occupying this space that is somehow up.
Like parallel to the earth down here, right?
You would be like, you don't mean that literally, right?
And if they said no literally,
then you'd be like,
uh, right?
Right?
Okay?
Bye.
See.
They say, oh God is just on this parallel time track to ours.
Yeah.
And not only does Noah ask any questions, I'll let us know and say you don't be literally
right?
They're like, oh yeah, yeah, no, that's true.
This weird assumption that God experiences time the same way we do.
Right.
He's existing in this moment.
And why do we say this is the ultimate sorry Calvinist and sorry Armenians and sorry,
you know,
Of course, William Craig is a molenist because he can't be normal.
Right?
Um.
Right.
Sorry molenists.
Sorry, open theus, sorry, on and on.
Right?
Yeah.
All of these positions at West with theology all have as a basic presupposition that God
exists at a point in time.
Okay.
question, does God know what's going to happen in the future?
is an incoherent question.
It is an incoherent question. There is not an answer to it because it's not
coherent.
Okay. It's like asking what color something is in absolute darkness. There is no
answer because the question does not make sense.
Yeah.
It's like asking what color is the number five?
Right, it's a category error.
It's an idko here at question.
There is no future for God.
God is not finite.
He does not exist in a point in time with more points of time,
potentially infinite points in time ahead of him.
That is absurd.
Okay, David, what?
Speaking atologically cool,
Right.
Uh, whatever you say, we have to speak ethylologically.
We have to speak ethically of God sometimes.
That's what we got.
And God speaks to us that way sometimes, right, to help us understand, because we're
humans.
As we said, we can only understand from our finite perspective.
But thinking that that's accurate, that that is literally accurate, right?
Is preposterous.
Okay.
Okay, so saying God chose
people in advance for salvation is in coherent.
Hmm.
Saying that he made that choice based on his foreknowledge,
equally if not more in coherent.
Saying that he's learning as he goes in coherent.
Yeah, deeply in coherent.
Right.
Because he doesn't go.
Okay.
Saying that he first saw all the possibilities
that arranged the black plague three card money
because you're a weird molinous,
like William late crack.
is incoherent.
Sorry.
Like this is all just incoherent.
It's not serious.
Yeah.
It's not serious guys.
I know you've been having these arguments for hundreds of years
but you've been wasting your time.
Bad news, okay.
It's all incoherent.
There is not a future for God.
There's not a past for God either.
Yeah.
Like do you think there's a past for God?
Like where he can look back and be like, ah, you know, hey, what would have happened if I had done this?
Like what?
Right you the God you're talking about is just a giant person
It's just a giant human yeah
Right with more common to the pagan's concept of God and the Christian concept of God
But notice also.
So, notice also, I was careful to do this.
We're not arguing for Plato.
We're not arguing for spheres and circles and tight circles.
Any of that.
We're not arguing for any of that either.
Right?
Like this is not Platonism.
Platonism got it wrong.
Right?
As well, maybe in the other direction or down a different side channel.
Temporal categories don't apply to God.
There's not a before an F.
after for God. Yeah. As God. So yes, all that kept probed anti-calvinist literature. You've
spent all that time reading was a waste of time. You should have been playing Marvel rivals or something.
Yeah, I mean the the I think the part of the reason why a lot of this language gets used.
for God is that in some way or another it's found in the scriptures, but the problem is
when you flip the lens around or whatever you want to say, and rather than using it as,
this is human beings' experience of what it's like to interact with God and instead say
this is what it's like for God to be God.
Right, you literalize it.
Let's talk about heaven as being a
there or something is fine unless you're serious. Right. Like if you run into someone, I'm sure
they're out there because flat earthers are out there who really believe that the heavens
are a dome and God knows the literal throne sitting on top of it. Right. We would say this is a
wacky person. Right. Because hey, yeah, the Bible speaks that way all over the place. Right. But
It's making that way poetic.
by analogy, not literally. Right? The sky is not a literal hard dome. Yeah. God has not
sit on a literal chair that is sitting on top of said dome. Right. Right. And pretty much no one
thought that it's not that oh yeah, that's what all those prohibitive thought, but now you know
modernists like father Andrew and father Steven now they say you know that's
just an out.
No, no everyone understood people, ancient people were not stupid.
Yeah.
Okay, they, they were just a, I would read the poetry of the Psalms.
It's great poetry.
Okay, like they understood poetry, illusions, imagery, they understood all this.
Okay, they were, they were, had the same kind of mind that you have.
Yeah.
Yeah, so.
All that said about God's timelessness.
Triple category of worries just don't apply to God.
Before and after don't apply to God.
There is no future for God. There is no past for God.
Right? God does not add a point in time.
He does not experience time as a succession of moments,
the way we do. Right?
Infinite or otherwise going backwards or forwards.
Um.
At the same time, Contra Plato, God does, and this isn't just analogy, God does the scriptures,
as is recorded in the scriptures, and in the history of the church.
God acts at particular times.
He does things at particular times.
And that's not just a time thing.
It's also a space thing. God is in particular places.
Right?
This is that weird puzzle we've pointed to a bunch on this show where it's like
Well, yeah, God is omnipresent
But he's also like really present in the tabernacle and the temple
He's like extra there. You're like wait, what?
Right? Like, how do those two things
We sit together.
That's where we're going tonight.
God acts in particular times and in particular places and is present in particular places.
God enters into human experience.
Now at no point can we try to figure out what it's like to be God and how God experiences
this because you don't know it's like to be a bat let alone God.
But we have this tension, because as Luchas said, God has God, the divine nature, right?
God, spatial and temporal categories don't apply.
Those are categories of human experience.
Nonetheless, right?
God appears to Abraham in a particular place at a particular time.
It appears, once a year, the tabernacle and then the temple.
bodily, even, at a particular time. So we have all of these episodes, the Old Testament,
where, despite God not existing in the sense of occupying points in time and space, where
God is described as, and talked about as occupying points in time and space.
That's a human experience.
Right.
So, how do we bridge that...
app right how could both of those be true how does that work and that's what we're
going to get into it our second half all righty well we are going to take a short break and we'll be right back
.
And we're back. This is the second half of this special pre-recorded Christmas episode
of the Lord of Spirits podcast. We're talking about the relationship of the incarnation
of Jesus Christ to time. And in our first half, we... I don't know. How do you even summarize
all that? But we kind of walked through. We talked about what eternity is. Yeah. What
What does eternity and what does it mean for God to be eternal?
You know?
So, temporal categories and spatial categories don't apply to God.
Yeah, that's basically the summary.
Yes, there is language and scripture that refers to God functioning in time, but that's
a human experience.
And we shouldn't, unlike the Calvinists, unlike, frankly, a huge amount of Western
satiriology consider that God is subject to time, especially not linear time.
So there we go.
That's a good summary.
Probably.
doesn't exist at a particular point in time and space,
but Bill does just talk about him doing things
at particular points at time and space.
And in bodily terms, is in occupying
a set of points in space at a point in time.
Yes, so now, we're going to talk about the incarnation,
because the fact is, if we really understand the incarnation,
which William Lane Craig doesn't, I'm just
to bash up the whole episode.
It's a dead horse, I know, but I'm at least on this show.
But if you understand the incarnation, right, then the incarnation provides us the key to
unlocking that dilemma completely because the incarnation of Christ is the entering of
God into human experience.
The definite article.
Yeah, the entry of God
God into human experience.
And we mean that it's several senses.
Okay.
So we mean that it is the paradigmatic entering, right?
It is the peak.
It is the pinnacle of God entering into human experience.
But we also mean it's the basis for all of it.
Right.
All of it is the incarnation.
Yeah.
Right.
and this is the only way...
to take on board the actual language of Scripture, especially the New Testament.
Right? No one has seen God at any time, says St. John, but the unique God who's in the
bosom of the fathers made him known. Right? He's not saying,
nor all those passages of the Old Testament where people saw God. He's saying,
that was Jesus.
Yeah. Yeah. Right. So Christ, and in particular, the incarnate Christ, is the means by which
right, that is possible through the whole testament. To get it more what we what we mean by that.
There is a basic problem, a basic foundational problem.
in, for example, Judaism and Islam.
There is a fatal flaw religiously, theologically speaking.
And that is that neither Judaism nor Islam can explain how God can communicate and interact
with humans.
Okay, what do you mean by that?
How can God within right rabbinic Judaism, non-Christian Judaism?
Yeah, we're not talking ancient Judaism here, we're talking yes.
Communicate about himself to humans truthfully so that humans can have some kind of understanding.
They'll probably say he speaks that he talks to us.
So, human language
language, finite historically contingent human language is capable of accurately describing
God.
I mean that would have to be the claim.
Well, no, there is no way they try to get around this because that's obviously a flawed claim.
Right.
Right?
Well, yeah, that's a problem.
is they would agree with Christians that God is ineffable.
That God cannot be accurately described in words in general.
So how do they try to get around this?
Well, you have to have an eternal language.
So what you do is you take A language, the case of rabbinic Judaism Hebrew, in the case
of Islam Arabic, specifically the Arabic of the Quran.
You take the text itself in the case of a lot of Islam and in the case of a lot of rabbinic Judaism the Torah or the Quran and you make that eternal.
Yeah.
So you say, well, it's not a finite human language.
It's divine language.
And because it's divine language, it can accurately carry God's self-revelation.
Here's the problem with
that. That doesn't solve the problem, right? Because the core problem was you have humanity
down here, finite. You have God up above, metaphorically, right? Infinite. All you've done
is take in language as a go-between and move it from the human side of the divider to the
Godside of the divider you haven't broken down the divider.
Yeah, and doesn't and doesn't rabbin
Judaism even say that the Torah itself exists before creation.
Yes. Islam says that about the Quran too. Yeah. Some forms of Islam.
The pre-eternal word meant hyper literally. Yes. Yes. So here's what I mean by that not
solving the problem. We just move to the other side of the divide. Like, okay, now you've got a
a device.
language that is eternal and infinite and therefore able to convey God, how can humans understand
that language? Right. I mean, that's... You've just moved the problem. Yeah. We understand it.
We understand it as like apparently some in Revenek Judaism will say that that Hebrew becomes
kind of limited at the Tower of Babel. But I mean, that just essentially says that there's a human
and he grew in a divine he...
through, you know, and that are related somehow.
That is it bridged.
Yeah.
Right.
And of course, then there's also just the very kind of obvious linguistic problem, which
is that we can, you know, linguists, especially philologists, watch these languages change over
time and you know have derivative elements and even stuff that's in the Torah right?
There's loan words in the Torah.
Yes.
Which is kind of a problem.
It's not even totally clear that the Quran is an Arabic.
It may be an Arabic.
Yeah.
An Arabic dialect.
It's not actually Arabic yet.
Yeah.
So that means it's on a line of linguistic development.
I mean, textual criticism presents big problems for both of those traditions.
If you're going to focus on those texts in that way.
Yeah.
And so this is a massive problem.
And it's a problem, pagans didn't have, right?
Because pagans don't worship infinite gods.
The gods they worship are finite.
So a finite god who's just bigger, right?
Essentially can reveal itself to a finite human,
just I mean, there's no issue there, right?
That's why we singled out or doubled out.
Judy is a bit Islam because Judy is a bit Islam.
I'm a bit of Judy is a bit Islam talk about an infinite God.
Right?
So they have this problem of how does an infinite God communicate with finite humans.
As Christians, we have the solution to this problem.
It is in the incarnation correctly understood.
in which God, the fullness of God, the infinite God,
Not a subset of God, not a reflection, not an emanation.
The fullness of God, the fullness of deity, everything it is to be God, right?
Becomes finite.
Becomes man.
Yeah.
Comes a mediator.
Bridges the divide.
Well, and even I recall in the long ago times when I was an undergraduate studying English
that one of my bolder professors talked about modern problems of language and
you know like deconstructionism and all that kind of stuff and said you know
that a lot of these writers they point to the fact that the word and the thing
that it's referring to or to use the technical language, the signifier and
the signified that there's a gap between them.
That when you say something that...
doesn't convey the thing, that just sort of points to the thing. And he said that what
a lot of these guys don't contend with is that Christ is the word who means himself,
that there is, that likewise, that there's no gap between, again, to use this technical
which signifier and signified that he actually does.
He is,
not spoken word, fully revealing himself,
not by just pointing at something else,
but by being himself.
I don't know if I'm expressing that well,
but I found that to be a useful way
of trying to understand what is very difficult to understand.
Right, yeah.
Yeah, so this is, yeah, so the point of the incarnation there,
right, the relationship between sign and thing,
signified is that
This is one of the rougher passages of St. Augustine,
but he kind of talks this way at one point.
This is, again, the correctly understood incarnation,
the doctor of the coronation is Christianity has
historically taught and believed it and dogmatized
into councils, right?
Says that Christ is not a human person
or Christ's humanity considered as a separate thing
is a pointer to who God is.
Right.
or a representation of who God is, but he is God.
And not at the expense of each other.
Right.
But so now that we've repeatedly used that phrase,
incarnation correctly understood.
Right. Obviously we can do a hundred episodes on this.
This is already kind of, I mean we've done more than what episode on Christology.
that are in Christology.
this is what we're taking a particular trajectory.
But just to quickly sort of summarize what we mean by Christology is it's not by the church.
Is that there is a second person of the Holy Trinity, the Sun, the divine logos,
the Word or wisdom right of God.
that he is begotten of the Father without reference to time.
So this is another thing. There's no before. Right? He's begotten. He's generated for the Father.
But with no, there's no before and after. I mean, the most you get is like before all ages,
But age is a reference to time itself.
Yes
So it's outside the boundary of time, right?
So there's no before and after right the the Sun is begotten
That's and that's what the father's all say again. This is a weird-bottomed thing. This is
All the way back right everyone who disagreed with areas
Yes.
And so, and he is the express image of the Father. Everything the Father is he is.
The only difference between he and the Father, right, the only difference between them is that he is begotten, and the Father is not.
And that divine person is made man.
That divine person takes upon himself human nature.
Now we talk about him taking upon himself human nature.
Again, there's some sloppy talk about this, right?
People will say, oh, he takes a human nature.
Is this sloppy talk?
Right.
Because you say he takes a human nature that makes it sound like a human nature makes it
sound like a thing.
Right.
And he adds this thing, or he attaches this thing to himself, or himself to this...
thing, right? Which, sorry William Lane Craig, is not how this works. Right? Human nature
is something that all humans share. The way that divine nature is something that the
three persons of the Holy Trinity share. Okay? So he takes upon himself our shared human
nature. What is the nature? Well, we've talked about this on the show a bunch, right?
We talked about how
The earlier language, the older language, so nature is a,
Fisis is a Greek term.
It really comes into Christian theology through Saint Paul
using it.
It's not used in the Greek translation
of the old Christian Old Testament.
For the most, I'm gonna not get into it.
There's an edge case, but it's not really used as a concept.
Okay, that the older language was body.
And if you've been listening to this show for very long,
You know how we...
define a body, in this case a nature, that it's a gathering of powers and potentialities.
It's sort of a cluster of powers and potentialities, a nexus of them.
And so Christ is a divine person, possesses the divine nature, powers, potentialities,
all of that of God. He adds to that.
The full set of human powers and potentialities, which includes a human body, which includes
a human soul, William Lanecrag, which includes the hair, so he's especially known for his
This is the cup of pollinator.
Yes, this is the cup of pollinator.
and includes a human will.
And include, right, all of that, right.
That also includes what are added, right?
He takes upon himself what are called the blameless passions.
We've talked about this before.
This is a distinction the fathers make, right?
So there are sinful passions, anger, lust, right.
There are also blameless passions, like getting tired
or hungry.
hungry, thirsty. Right. And would include passions the way we think of the passion of Christ,
right? We're able to be injured, harmed. Right. Christ voluntarily accepts those. Right.
He allows those to happen to him. Right. But again, that is additive. Right. That is
And why am I making this big point of additive? Well, so there's a lot of folks out there
Some of them well-meaning
some of them clueless
Who
Take the use of the word Kenosis in Philippians to like way too seriously. Oh, yeah, they'll say stuff like well
He set aside being God or he set aside his
powers as God or like
Like, no.
No, no, stop it
Stop it God does not stop being God
Right he had no way stopped being God at any point
Right he was everything he always was plus
Plus these human powers and potentialities plus allowing himself to suffer these blazing
Right, that's what I mean by additive plus
Right.
There's the prayer that we say a lot as priests talking about Christ when he died, when his
human soul was separated from his human body.
That Christ, we say that Christ's body was in the grave, his soul was in Hades harrowing
it.
And he was on the throne with the father and the Holy...
spirit in the grave of the body, but in his and was God in paradise with the feet. Yeah, yeah. Yeah.
Right. Fill y'all so
he didn't stop being God
Okay, and
the reason part of the reason I think why people go down that road is
again
Humans rejecting what's beyond their understanding, right?
which is, well, wait a minute, how could he be like?
omnipresent. Yeah. And standing there. Right.
Egalily and walking from place to place, cross it. Like we just said,
finite, crossing points in, right, how can he be infinite and finite at the same
time? Yeah. And I think right one of the things that probably
gets people in the trouble with regards to this, when they're when they are
reading it right in the sense that they realize that Kenos does not mean
that he's...
stopped being God or he's less God or anything like that. There's the language in scripture
of him being the same yesterday, today and forever. And then also the language in our
himnography of that he is incarnate without change. So it is correct to read that as meaning,
he's still God in every way, completely. He's still the son of God in every way. But as we'll see,
It actually means more than that.
Yeah.
Emptying is about his suffering and his humiliation.
Is his clear in context, but you read the whole hymn.
Yeah, yeah, yeah.
Right, it's what there.
Emptying himself, he was a humbling himself, even unto death.
Death out across his humiliation, his suffering, his death.
That's the emptying it's talking about.
Not that he stopped being God.
Take that a little too literal.
is the problem. We have trouble understanding how he could be finite and
infinite at the same time. Yeah. How he could be everywhere and also, well there
he is at that synagogue in Galilee and now he's walking from Capurna, Umba,
St. Up. Right. Here's the point I want to make. That's the way God has described
all through the Old Testament.
Yep, that's right.
As being, both everywhere,
and in the Holy of Holies.
Or both everywhere and sitting down at the table with Abraham.
Right.
On and on and on.
Yeah. Right.
Walking over with Abraham to look at Sodom.
Right.
That's the way he's described all through the Old Testament.
If we didn't understand the incarnations,
until the incarnation is revealed to us,
Gospels until the incarnation is revealed to us. That is just a mystery.
That is just a contradiction that makes no sense in the Old Testament.
That God has presented his infinite and finite at the same time that he's presented as being unable to be seen and then he's seen by people at the same time.
These all of these things are just these contradictions at paradoxes in the Hebrew Bible.
And when the incarnate
is revealed to us, all of a sudden we see how that's possible.
Yeah, I think it's all of the language we're referring to right now that comes
from the councils and stuff is descriptive.
Yeah.
It's just a long series of, oh!
Yeah, I think it's worth underlining and we'll talk way more about this, but it's
worth underlining the language that you just used about the incarnation being
being.
revealed to us. Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. It's almost like I did that deliberately. Hey, there's a madness to my method.
So, right. And so we have God, right? This also solves the problem we were talking about with Islam and rabbinic Judaism,
because God is now able to be seen and touched and spoken with and inner
interacted with by humans.
He is revealed.
Christ's humanity is the bridge.
Between God and man.
Literally.
And further this explains how we've talked about this before.
all the way way back in the long ago time to our episode about God's body.
We talked about how a lot of times we get it backwards,
people will say that the Bible uses anthropomorphic language
to describe God.
Right.
But really, from the perspective of the scriptures,
from the perspective of man being made in the image of God,
actually, it talks about humanity in theomorphic terms.
So my right arm is just a
reflection of the strong right arm of God. Right. Yeah. Right. Which is the reality. Right. So,
at the beginning of our first half, we sort of posed this problem. Right. The problem of God being
described in the Old Testament throughout the Scriptures as being both sort of finite and infinite
at the same time. This half we talked about how the incarnation solves that.
And now, as we come back to the temporal element, we come back to time, we're going to sort
of narrow in on a particular aspect of this problem.
And that's going to be what we talk about in the third half.
And so here's that sort of sub-problem, right?
Christ in his post-resurrection appearances.
Right. One of the common features, and if you go to Mattins regularly, Sunday
Mattins, you hear all of these over and over again. Which you should go
readings. You should go you guys. There are some churches where you look out at
the beginning of Mattins or Throws, and there's no one there. I have to just
give a nice little shout out to the church in Raleigh, North Carolina, where I'm
about to go. Last time I was there, I looked out at the beginning of Mattins, there
There's like 85 people standing there waiting for it to begin.
like am I in the twilight zone here?
How is this a thing?
But then there were probably 387 people
once the liturgy started.
That's right.
So to be fair, there is,
there is no what outside the Orthodox church?
There is no parking outside the Orthodox church.
Yes.
Yes, sorry.
Yeah.
Go to Matt and Zerbio.
Go to the post.
Nello Parkus.
Yeah.
So.
The uh...
So, but a common feature in all of these, right, when Christ appears to his disciples is,
and this is twofold, part one is Handle Me in C, which was, we literally heard, this
past Sunday, Handle Me in C for a spirit has not flesh and bones that you see that I
have, right?
So, and another very, you know, St. Thomas is another variation of that, right?
See the...
Put your finger right touch me. Yeah, I have a physical body
And this is presented as proof that Christ is really risen from the dead that he's not a spirit. He's not a ghost
His he's really still embodied right and then the other piece of that is
Christ eating in front of them right eating fish eating a honeycomb right
These things and these are all there pretty much everybody agrees
That's why they're there there there to show that it's a bodily resurrection. He's
experience the bodily resurrection. Okay. And obviously implied in its
own cases outright stated is that if this was a spirit like God or an angel or
something or a ghost, you could not touch it and it could not eat. Right. But remember
back there the Old Testament. Some of those times when God was described as
finite, we see him touching people in eating. Right. Yeah. And
and relatedly, there's the question of like like, you know, we
already made reference to the hospitality of Abraham, if you
keep reading that passage, and especially the beginning of
the chapter that follows, you know that it's it's God and two
angels who had
showed up and sat down. And so you might ask the question like, okay, well, this is it,
they all ate. What does that mean exactly? So you're saying, well, God is eating because
of what we're about to talk about. But the angels, what's going on there? And there is actually an
explanation for this not found in that passage, but elsewhere in the Old Testament scriptures,
namely in the book of Tobit, where the archangel Ruff
fail, accompanies some of the main characters, and the question is raised, hey, you know,
buddies in disguise as a human.
You know, hey, buddy, what's the deal with you eating if you're just an angel?
Because they all agree, you know, angels don't eat.
And the archangel says, well, it just appeared that I was eating.
You know, this is just an illusion.
And so taking that paradigm and applying it to the hospital of Abraham, what you get is
God.
Eating because he's got a human body and two angels appearing to eat that best
So but yeah, we'll we'll obviously break out all the rest of that stuff
Yes, we go, but so to put a finer point on this okay
What is this wrong? This is may not seem like a big problem to you at first
Okay, whatever you know God's God he can do it every once right?
it. Okay. Imagine you're arguing with it.
Dositist. Okay. You can do this with the actual original Jewish Dositist so you can do this with
any, just about any Nostek who has a de Setic view of Christ. Dositism comes from Dakeo
to Seam or to appear, right, and the idea is that they believe that Christ just appeared to be human.
Please.
not actually incarnate. And the Dostodist says to you, especially if it's one of the originals,
the Jewish Dostodists, they say to you, okay, yeah, Jesus in the Gospels, right? They're
going to say to you, Jesus in the Gospels is just a theophity like the Old Testament.
Right. Right. What is the argument? What is the argument that all the church fathers use against that?
The A B-drank
people physically touched him.
He had physical wounds.
So if the Bassa says to you,
yeah, look here, no testament.
There's God eating and drinking and touching people.
The angel of the Lord,
let's say they agree with you.
The angel of the Lord is Christ.
Sure, the angel of the Lord is Jesus.
That's the same person.
And look, when he appears
before they quote unquote it
cardation quote unquote before the quote unquote incarnation right he they'll say to you uh he
touches people at ease so see that is improved that uh he was really incarnate
yeah that's why there's a problem that's why there's a problem here yeah yeah
And the counter-argued by the fathers still the same.
It's no.
he, him eating and drinking and touching people proves that he's incarnate.
Here he is. Yep. Yep.
All right, well on that bombshell, we're going to take our second and final break.
How did the sun cross once carried by the pagans of the Baltic North become the cross of Jesus?
How did the last pagan nation of medieval Europe first encounter Christ in the Orthodox
Church?
Brought to you said these people were known the swerves.
Come with us on a pilgrimage through the sometimes strange, sometimes surprising street
of the Dwayne.
The green-norded land poised to peace and west.
Hey, welcome back.
It's our special Christmas pre-requited episode of The Lord of Spears podcast, here December
25th, 2025.
There's something kind of beautifully numerically rhyming about that.
And we're talking about the incarnation of Jesus Christ and its relationship to time in
particular.
So we just...
finished the second half, talking about the the handle me and see problem, the
fact that Christ points to the materiality of his body as proof of his bodily
resurrection. And then we connect that, of course, to the fact that there are
handle me and see moments in the Old Testament as well, that God does
things that are
experienced materially through a body. They're in the old testament. So we're
gonna then talk about exactly how that can be. How is it that handle me and see
can show up in both old and new testament. So where do we go from here,
Father? Well, so we have to talk about another aspect of the incarnation. Okay.
in the last...
We talked about the incarnation from the top down, the movement downward of the divine person,
of the sun, the divine logos becoming man.
And now, if you go at it from the other direction, moving upward, I.e. that Christ by taking
upon himself our humanity and Christ being God.
deifies our humanity. So what does that mean? Yes, the downward movement that we talked about last
time, or last half, is the prerequisite of the upward movement. Christ comes out to us so that he
can then elevate us. And this is right there in the New Testament.
it. Logus, Classicus, for it is Ephesians 4, 9 and 10.
All right, so in Ephesians 4 verses 9 and 10, we read this, in saying he ascended,
what does it mean but that he had also descended into the lower regions, the
earth. He who descended is the one who also ascended far above all the heavens, that he
He might fill all things.
And often when this is translated, it's put into parentheses as a kind of aside.
Do you think that's right that it should be in parentheses?
I know.
No.
Because certainly in the manuscripts, there's no parentheses.
There's hardly any punctuation at all.
Yeah.
No.
He's just repeating his argument essentially.
You
an opposition as a, as a, there's a downward movement
than an upward movement.
This is standard.
So remember, say Paul's thinking in a Semitic language.
Right?
Parallelisms, right?
But this, this idea, right, if you're familiar even vaguely
with Orthodox theology, say, Nathanacious on the incarnation,
You
quote, God became man so that man might become God. Right. That the purpose of Christ's descent
was the elevation of humanity. Yeah. I mean, in the verse right before this, it talks about,
it says, you know, when he ascended on high, he led a host of captives and he gave gifts to men.
Yes, which is well, we would...
We'll go down that rabbit hole right now.
Right.
St Paul does something interesting with the Old Testament quote there.
But yeah, yeah.
You're tempting me to rabbit trail.
Yeah.
Maybe this will be our next step.
Here's the one keeping me on task.
I will, you know.
I don't only have to keep you on task,
but keep you generating new episodes
so that people can have those five more years
that you promised what was it last time or the time before?
I made no such promise.
That's my recollection.
But so the this is also expressed at say basal the great express is the same thing talking about
Man be created in the image of God as man being that being that created being that is commanded to become God
Hmm, right?
Now obviously
such a thing
Right? Or St. Peter saying that we become partakers of the divine nature.
Such a thing is only conceivable because of Christ in the incarnation.
Right? I think about it once again. If we just take St. Basil's statement literally,
okay, you are commanded, become God. What's step one?
Right?
Yeah, right. So this is clearly the
the way some of our Protestant friends would like to read it. They'd have to hear
commanded, right? Works righteous as for something, right? Like what would be the
works that you do to become God? Right. Well, and even like even within the
pagan context, I mean, number one, pagans do not understand God in any of the
terms that we just talked about. You're right. Right. For them, gods are just
very, basically very big, very powerful.
Not...
humans exactly. But it's just how do you get big? Yeah, exactly. And certainly humans do become
gods in paganism. Most of course do not. It is a tiny, tiny, tiny, tiny little fraction of a
fraction of a fraction who get to do that. And but the the great works that people do
don't gain them godhood. It is that the gods see the works you do and say,
We will give Godhood to this one.
You know, yeah, but all they're giving you is like more power. Right. You don't become
the infinite God because there is no infinite God in that in that frame. Yes. The ones who
would grant it are finite. Right. It's just like you can join their club. They don't
have themselves. Right. But so this is only possible because of Christ. It's only possible
because of who Christ is, that in Christ's person he is...
perfectly united God to humanity.
That then makes it possible through God's grace,
through divine action, right, for people to become God.
We're gonna talk about what that means,
but a piece of that on the way, right,
is what St. Basil the Great says regarding
the creation of man in God's image,
is commanded to become God.
As we've said, that's only possible because
of Christ's incarnation. So even though Christ's incarnation had not been revealed, nobody knew about it directly, right?
At the time of the creation of the world, because at the time of the creation of the world, the creation of man, obviously there was nobody to know it except God himself, right? Like the...
But, right?
Christ's incarnation then is being
positive by saying.
basil. Right? And how he understands what we made in the image of God means, that Christ's
incarnation is the basis for the creation of humanity. Yeah. Which is the reason that
for the promo image for this episode, and we've used this before in other contexts, but
icon is of Christ creating Adam in a big mosaic.
from before the Great Schism.
And if you look at traditional Orthodox icons
of the creation of Adam, it's Christ creating Adam,
and they have the same face that they look like
identical twins, so that Christ is himself,
as you said, the basis for the creation of Adam.
Right, right.
And so what the Father said, what we're saying here,
is that Christ is the cause of the creation of humanity.
in all senses.
Yeah.
Right? In the sense of purpose, right?
Because humanity is created with the purpose
we talk about the image of God in terms of purpose.
Right? Of...
the evocation of Himself in the world. Right?
Transfiguration of the world. That's only possible because of the incarnation.
So the purpose of Adam before the fall,
the purpose of Him being created. Right?
Right.
requires the incarnation to be true, or it's not possible.
Right, so in terms of purpose,
in terms of being the one who actually did it,
the efficient cause, that's Christ too.
Right, all things are made through him,
without him was not anything made that was made,
that includes humanity.
Right, the formal cause, right?
Right? Christ's humanity is the paradigm for-
or humanity or shared humanity.
We share it with him, right?
So his humanity is logically prior
to Adam's humanity.
Right, say that again for all the kids in the back.
Christ, humanity is logically prior
to Adam's humanity.
Yes.
Yep.
Adam's humanity is a reflection of Christ's humanity.
Theomorphic.
is the image, yes, of Christ humanity.
Theo Amphropo, I don't know how to work that out.
Yeah.
If you want to do a deep dive into this,
read St. Mark the Ascetic of the Filicalia,
where he talks about the...
Kiriakos Anthropos.
The Lordly Man.
So...
So we were talking about Christ's resurrection body at the end of the last half, right,
in terms of this problem, right, or proposed problem, right, that it could be handled and
touched right that he eats right but something else
that you very clearly see in those same resurrection appearance accounts of Christ.
In fact, a point is made of this, is that Christ's resurrected body has a different relationship
with space than his body did before his crucifixion.
Yeah, it's clear that for instance he just
appears in rooms with the doors being closed.
The doors being closed, a detail that is mentioned very explicitly in that text.
Explicitly, yes.
That Christ did not cross all the intervening points in space to get from point A to point
B. And also that, whereas, I was going to say all through the Gospels, we see him walking
from point A to point B.
Yeah, and getting tired and all that kind of stuff.
But also as we covered in our episode about the post-resurrection appearances.
For whatever reason a lot of people don't recognize him, that he seems to look different than
he used to.
Yeah.
If you want to know more about that, go back and do the archives.
Yep.
We talk about that recognition.
Yeah.
And so Christ we see has it now, his humanity, right?
including as you would buy it has a different relationship with space than it did before and this of course is what Christians have always
pointed out
Here's another sorry Calvinists
The early Calvinist tradition had a big problem with this
Saga to Luther the Lutherans
Hey, but
How can Christ's body be on all those altars and all those churches at the same time?
Yeah.
If it's a human body.
So let's not even talk theologically.
Just look at the resurrection appearances.
Like Christ does not need to cross in a reading space.
Like he can be.
Christ is everywhere. That includes his humanity.
But within Calvinist theology, there's this thing called the extra Calvinisticum,
where they literally argue that Christ...
divine nature is everywhere and as human nature is only in one place.
Wait.
Wow.
The Christ body is seated at the right hand of God, which is seated as a place.
Somewhere in 3D space.
And so his divinity extends farther than his humanity.
And even Martin Luther could see that was historian, but our
Alvinous friends.
don't, or don't care. But yes, right? So Christ, it's everywhere. It's the whole Christ,
right? Who is everywhere? So what does that mean? Well, you know, just to use straight
theological terms, that means Christ's human-
humanity is now participating, partaking, of his divine omnipresence.
Quadivinity, spatial categories never applied to Christ.
Now, his resurrected body, right?
His resurrected body.
body, his resurrected humanity, his ascended humanity, spatial categories, no longer
applied to his humanity either.
Yep.
Right?
So, that space, how about time?
And so what we're positive here, what solves this whole problem.
problem. What the Father saw is that the same way that those spatial categories, that spatial
finitude no longer applies to Christ's humanity, right? Temporal categories which never applied
to Christ's Quad Divinity, also no longer applied to his humanity. There's no before and
after. Therefore the incarnate Christ
can create Adam. The incarnate Christ can eat with Abraham. But it is still true that
he became incarnate in the womb of the Thay of Tocos. Those two do not contradict each
other in any way, shape or form. Because human nature is created in finite, but in union
and with Christ, be...
comes infinite by partaking of the divine nature. And so when we think about, right, we're
told over and over again in the New Testament that our future destiny in the bodily resurrection
as humans, what that looks like, what our salvation looks like in the life of the world
to come. It's something we can't.
comprehend now. Right? So then we can't fully understand. Probably because parts have been
involved in things being infinite. Right? But the resurrected Christ is always
positive. His humanity is always positive as our window, our glimpse, right, of what
that will be like. We will be like him. Right. And so...
This means we have to change our thinking
about what eternity looks like for us.
So it doesn't make sense for us
to view eternity as just,
oh, we're gonna have an endless succession of moments
going into the future.
Right.
So that's not what eternity is for God.
And us being made eternal is us coming to partake in the divine nature.
It is us becoming like Christ, like Christ's humanity.
And Christ's humanity is not experiencing an endless succession of moments.
Yeah, and even if we posit that that's what the life of the age to come is for humans,
then it's essentially saying that the dividing wall between God and man remains,
that you
incarnation didn't happen. Didn't do it. Yeah. Yeah. And it's certainly not some kind of
platonic stasis. Yeah. Staring at the Orbor otherwise. Long time listeners will know what
I'm referring to. Long time Roman Catholic listeners will probably nash their teeth at that again.
Yes.
Yep.
It is also not like a big circle, like a big cycle that repeats itself.
Right like yeah, it's the same thing. It's none of that
It's none of that well, what is it well? We don't know that's where we started remember
We only know what it's like to be finite yeah
We don't know what it's like to partake of the infinite I mean there's that's what we're gonna do there's
We get glimpses of it in this life
You know, but it's but it's just glimpses and you can't really grasp it
What is it?
Is it like to not occupy a particular point in space?
To not have to cross intervening distances
to get from one place to be in one place
and that'd be in another place?
I mean, the closest thing...
I don't know what that's like.
The closest that human beings get to that,
in any kind of, I don't know,
palpability as it were,
is some of the ecstacies of the saints, you know?
Yeah, same.
Paul being caught up in the state that by locate.
Yeah, yeah.
But they didn't tell us what that's like.
Right.
They didn't.
We just occasionally get testimonies to it.
You know, even St. Paul when he describes his experience of being caught up, he says he
heard things that are that cannot be uttered by humans.
Like, yeah.
He's like, oh, he's about to, he's about to, you know, open, pull back the veil.
It's just a couple.
Let us know what it's like.
Yeah, could you utter a little bit, buddy?
But no, no.
Because I think it's
because it's unutterable, because it's not a thing that could be said.
Right. It's not a thing that we as FIdex can understand until we're there and we're doing it.
Right. Like yeah.
And so we just have to accept that there is no model based in our finitude that explains the infinite.
There can't be.
Definitially.
Yeah.
Right. But the other place where we see this and think about this where this has to shape
our thinking is in terms of the saints. Right. So one of what I was going through in
whole council of God, the book of Revelation, where the things that broke people's brains
is that I pointed out that according to pretty much all the earliest interpreters, this
is pretty well locked in. The 24 human elders who say John sees.
worshiping in heaven, right, are the 12 patriarchs, right, from the tribes of
Israel and the 12 apostles. Everybody's like, oh yeah, okay, that makes it, you
know, 24, 12 apostles. But if you pause for a second, you may remember that St.
John is one of the 12 apostles, right? So he was seeing himself in glory.
He was seeing himself.
in what was from his perspective as a finite human the future. But it's not
presented as seeing the future, it's presented as seeing the present. And then
you remember St. Paul says in Ephesians that we are already seated with Christ
in the heavenly places. Yeah.
Right? So this isn't an idea that had to develop the idea of
as we've been talking about it tonight,
is whether you can conceive of just by negation.
Just here's what we experience.
God is not that.
You don't need a really superdeveloped philosophical system
to get this.
This also answers the really silly objection
that some of our sillier Protestant friends sometimes use,
which is
How could the saints hear all those prayers? Here's why I say this is silly, right?
They're positing that the soul of a departed saint
hears prayers based on sound waves passing through the atmosphere, right?
At this be like 775 miles an hour from you to them.
Is anyone claiming that?
No, no one is claiming that that's how the saints hear prayers.
Right?
Like, literally no one thinks that.
Why would a departed saint not be able to hear five people praying at the same time?
They're not hearing with years.
Right?
This is...
again, projecting our finitude to see if they have some kind of blue force ghost body or something.
It haven't. Right. Right. Like, or something. I don't know. I don't know how that would work.
But yeah. So yeah, we see in the saints and the saints, right? Saint Nicholas kept for a long
time kept popping up places.
Yeah, even while life out at sea.
We have appearances of saints, right?
You know, folks, especially folks who are North Island, get all excited when
when we say that they Otoco is shown up somewhere. But like there's lots of other
saints who show up places, right?
St John, glimicking St John of the ladder when he was the abbot of the monastery
about Sinai like had Moses stop by had I mean a whole bunch
saints, right? This is part of Christianity, right? And why could they do that? Well, because
as saints, right, their humanity has been conformed to Christ's humanity, which is perfectly
united to divinity, which means it is no longer finite, it is partaking of the infinite.
growing to the fullness of the stature of Christ.
And so yeah.
hopefully this episode because we get lots of questions because we keep eluding to it in different episodes.
Uh, this idea of the relationship between the eternal and the incarnation and people who,
uh, right. And, uh, right.
I think the first time I mentioned it on the show, uh,
Pazzo mentioned that he had been listening to that and was like,
thought to himself, will father Steven go there and then of course, like the cool aid man,
burst through the wall and yelled at it.
Oh yeah.
So yeah, but so we thought it appropriate.
In the piece of the Nativity, it's obvious connection to the incarnation of Christ.
Now it'd be a good time to spend a little time, because maybe one of our shorter episodes
actually.
We stayed kind of on task.
to lay out sort of the argument and the understanding behind that.
just alluding to it and tantalizing the listener.
So hopefully not that we've exhaustively explained it, there's plenty to ruminate on, but I think
we've laid out sort of the basic concept, at least as clearly as we've ever done.
I like the fact that for this episode the place that we ended it is with the saints because
It's one of the principles of Orthodox theology that...
Christology and Soteriology are distinct and yet completely indivisible theological discourses,
as it were, not that they're reducible to discourses, but you know what I mean?
That if you understand who Christ is, then we understand who the saints are.
And we also understand what our own
task is as Christians.
Right. This is, you know, we don't only did a couple of, uh, sorry, Calvinists for this
episode, but I mean, this is one of the problems.
This is, this is the problem.
Well, I shouldn't say the problem.
This is one of the many problems with Calvinism is that Calvinism, of course, is
mainly the thing that most people will think about it is that it's a
surgery, right?
Monarchism.
And I mean, there's literally websites with that as their title, pushing Calvinist
So, the theology, you know, the
idea that it is God alone and God is the only one doing anything about salvation.
Right? But the thing that they don't seem to realize is that whatever you
positive about Soteriology has an analog, not just an analog, a basis in your
your Christology. So if monogism is true about
of theology, then mono-energism must be true about Christology. In other words, that Christ
has only one energy, meaning that he's not actually really human, because if he doesn't
have human energies, he has only divine energies, then he's not fully human. And so that's
One of the big reasons why...
My Calvinism tends towards Nestorianism because it posits this kind of disjunction between
the divine Christ and the human Jesus, not explicitly.
Not explicitly.
Most Calvinists would not affirm this Storianism.
But nonetheless, it's baked into the Soteriology.
Where that's really important for most Christians who think God don't care about those particular
debates.
is that when we begin to understand the incarnation as eternal and as manifesting at a particular point,
as revealing at a particular point in human history, then we see what the Christian life is about.
It means that it's not only about what will happen in what is for us the future. In other words,
Do I go to heaven when I
die, which of course we've talked about ad nauseam, why that is not a correct eschatology.
But you know what I mean? It's not just about what happens to you when you die. Although
it is about what happens to you when you die. But that the infinite God and the infinite
possibility of human exaltation, elevation, salvation, defecation is available to us right
right now. Right now.
One of the things that is said by kind of pop anti-Christianity is, you know, you're going
to live this whole life, this particular way, hoping that something will be different
for you after you die, that you're going to get rewarded in heaven, right?
And I mean, that's not based on nothing.
Certainly our experience here and now is that there's elements in the future, that the
life of the age to come is to come that it's
not now, but it is also now. The basic gospel message, repent for the kingdom of God is at hand,
doesn't mean it's just coming next. It means it's present. It's present because Christ is the kingdom
of God. He is the king. And so his kingly influence, his kingly reign is wherever he is. And so
So in as much as we are in Christ as the sentence scripture, the kingdom of God is within you.
you. And when we begin to grasp that or just at least to acknowledge it, what that does
for me and maybe it does for you, listener, is an inspiring sense of wonder in you. Wonder.
the infinite God, the God who is beyond time, beyond...
who cannot be captured, who cannot be understood, whose ways are higher than our ways.
That God enters into the womb of his mother, the Virgin Mary,
that in that entrance he becomes truly man, and that he's born, and in this feast
we see him not just a baby in a manger.
but we see God in a manger.
We see the one whose will upholds all of creation as the most vulnerable, helpless state of
what it means to be human.
And that's astonishing.
And also because as I said, Christology and Sotiriality always go together.
but also that as we participate in Him,
as we are faithful to Him, as we partake in Him,
that we begin to transcend the boundaries of our createdness.
And I find that a profoundly comforting and even relieving thought,
that the mercy of God is such,
that the sins that I have, the weak
this is that I have, the utter failures that I have, all of the flaws that I have are transcendable
by kneeling at the manger of Christ, kneeling at the altar of God,
God, giving my life to him obeying his commandments.
that in that we, to use the language of the Church of others, become uncreated, become
God. And because we are finite, then that means that it is an infinite road, that this
life is not the only time of progress in this, but that the life of the age to come is
is also a life of progress.
us. See the great love that God has for us? It's impossible to imagine, impossible to fathom,
and yet here we are. And that's why even the greeting that we have in your Therak's Church,
which comes from one of our greatest sets of hymns, the canon for the Nativity,
Contains within it.
Everything that we just said actually in a very compact form Christ is born.
Glorify Him.
That the infinite one is born.
That He is human.
And we glorify Him. We glorify Him because He is God.
God and in glorifying him, then we also participate in his.
glory. So that's what I have to say about all of that.
Yes, so of course, being an aneokian priest, right, we also say, crisis born glorify him in Arabic.
Once I learned that, you know, it was or leave to me because I found out when all those people were
calling me Mijnu and they were wishing me a Merry Christmas.
There's an inside baseball joke.
Yeah.
The ball portrait of our listeners will get.
And you can always spot the Egyptians because they call you Mugnoon.
So I thought about spoiling the series finale of The Good Place.
Is it in control?
I'm not going to do that.
I'm not going to resist my darker urges in this regard.
That's poil it.
But I think one thing that's often missing when we talk about time is because we're kind
and denial of this, is the relationship between time and death.
You know, we made a lot of comparisons this episode between temporal categories and spatial
categories, categories of time and categories of space.
And in spatial terms, you know, the spatial term that becomes a problem is distance.
Distance between people.
Distance between things.
a complication but you know where.
We've got a lot of tech may to help us overcome distance
Whether we're talking about you know airline travel
To physically cross great distances high speed rail whatever or we're talking about the internet
Right means of communication that we have to cross
physical distances and reconnect people and things
But we're sort of powerless in the face of time
And it turns to the relationship between time and death, time kills everything.
Every moment in our life ends.
Sometimes that's good, right?
Moments of pain, agony, mourning, horror, difficulty, struggle.
moment's end.
They die.
But so does every moment of beauty, peace, love, and joy in our life.
Because we're finite.
Time rolls on.
Things end.
And that's a constant.
We can't bring people back to life.
at least I can't. Some of the saints can in some select cases, but you know what I mean.
We can't return to a better moment in the past. It all just sort of goes away.
And in the face of that, then there is this face.
when we think about what the resurrection means.
The resurrection of our bodies, the resurrection of the world.
Because frankly, if you talk to most people who identify as Christians,
first of all they won't even be talking about the life of the world to come
or the bodily resurrection. They'll be talking about going to heaven.
But you're talking to them about the
positive version of the afterlife, right? The good place.
What eternal life looks like. And the idea you get is that, well,
I'm going to live forever but sort of, right? Because especially if they're among our
Protestant friends, but even among a lot of our Roman Catholic friends, and unfortunately,
even some of our orthodox rids probably who are for taking it in this.
They've had baked into them to one degree or another that most of their identity is sin.
Right?
You know, they don't believe in total depravity, right?
As such. Right.
They have this idea that pretty much every aspect of their personality and their life and everything is touched by sin.
And why that's an issue is that the them who they think is going to live forever, right?
the me who's gonna live forever.
How was-
is that actually going to look like the actual me? Once you take everything sinful out of it,
what I've been told, that almost everything I do and think is sinful. But so something
corresponding to me or some version of me is going to experience some endless succession
of moments in someplace nice.
There's just gonna be nice.
Happy forever.
That's not a lot of hope.
It's never been out what Scripture teaches, fortunately.
That's not Christianity, but that's not a lot of hope either.
But the consequence of what we've talked about tonight is different than that.
It means that the promise of the resurrection, not just of ourselves, but of the whole creation,
of everything God created, it doesn't just all go away.
Is that all of those moments, all of those times, all of those places, all of those things,
everything that was good, everything that was beautiful, everything that was joyous.
Every experience of peace
While it seems to have died to us
In our finitude in this life
It is all going to come back
That is all going to be made eternal
And all of the other stuff that dies that time kills
Pain, suffering, sorrow.
difficulty. All that stays dead. All of that is gone. And everything that stopped you and I,
everything that's been holding us back, everything that's been making it a struggle and making it hard,
or just straight out stopping us and blocking us from being good, from being joyous, from
being at peace, from being beautiful.
All those hindrances, all those difficulties, all those barriers are going to be gone.
And we're going to be free to be those things and free to be those things eternally.
In a state where time will never take them away.
time will never draw them to a close, time will never separate us from each other.
That's the promise that we have in the resurrection of Christ.
That's the promise that we have in Christ taking our humanity into Himself.
That's the promise of theosis.
That's the promise of salvation.
The Christ in who He is as we participate in Him being born on this day as you're hearing
this.
That's what it's all about.
So that's what I have to say.
Amen.
Well, that's our Christmas special.
Thank you very much everyone for listening.
We love to get email and messages through Facebook and so forth.
So you can contact us at LordofSpirits.AncientFate.com.
You can send us a message through our Facebook page.
You can also leave us a voicemail at SpeakPipe.com slash LordofSpirits.
And if you have basic questions about Orthodox Christianity
or you need help to find a parish in the 3D world,
which is where we do all this stuff, go to Orthodoxintro.org and get some help.
Enjoy this world!
broadcast on the second and fourth Thursdays of the month at 7 p.m. Eastern 4 p.m. Pacific,
go ahead baby, go ahead, go ahead and light up the town, and maybe do anything your heart
desires.
And if you are on Facebook, you can follow our page there, you can join our discussion
group, and please leave us a review wherever you listen to this podcast, and more importantly,
share this show with one of your friends who is going to benefit from it.
And finally be sure to go to AncientFraith.com.
and help make sure we and lots of other AFR
podcasters stay on the air.
Remember, I'll always be around, and I know.
I know like I told you so many times before,
you're gonna come back.
Thank you, good night, Merry Christmas.
You've been listening to the Lord of Spirits
with Orthodox Christian priests,
Father Andrew Stephen Damick,
and Father Stephen DeYoung,
a listener-supported presentation.
of ancient faith radio.
And I beheld and I heard the voice of many angels round about the throne and the beasts
and the elders, and the number of them was 10,000 times 10,000 and thousands of thousands
saying with a loud voice worthy as the land that was slain to receive power and riches
and wisdom and strength and honor and glory and blessing.
Revelation chapter 5 verses 11-12.